Much is said of Sao Paulo's multiculturalism
On parle bien de Sao Paulo, de son multiculturalisme,
and of its diverse population,
des plusieurs populations qui y habitent,
but very little is spoken of the black population.
mais on parle peu de la population noire.
Why? The historical process in in Sao Paulo has been different
Pourquoi ?
from Rio de Janeiro's and Salvador's, that were capital cities.
À Sao Paulo le procès a été différent du Rio et de Salvador, qui étaient des capitales.
In Sao Paulo, the black population still arrived in great numbers
À Sao Paulo la population noire rentre fortement
when slavery had already started to be called into question. With the
dans un moment où l'esclavage est déjà contesté
beginning of the coffee surge and the ending of the international slave trade,
c'est-à-dire, après le cycle du café et la fin du trafic international,
from where did the biggest share of the black population come from?
d'où vient la plupart de la population noire de Sao Paulo ?
It came from the so called interprovincial slave trade,
Ça vient de l'appelé trafic interprovincial.
by which black people who were dismissed from Rio's and northeast plantations
Bon, c'est les noirs qui étaient dispensés des labours du Rio et du Nordeste en crise
and sent here to Sao Paulo.
et ils sont restés par ici.
Every city with a big share of black population
Toutes les villes qui avaient un grand contingent de la population noire
has gone through massive processes of gentrification,
sont passés par un grand procès de gentrification,
racial and social segregation.
ségrégation ethnique, ségrégation social.
It couldn't have been different with Sao Paulo.
Sao Paulo ne pouvait être diffèrent.
However, we also know
Mais, comme on sait aussi
that capitalism has developed in the most literal meaning of the word
c'est ici à Sao Paulo que le capitalisme va se développer
here in Sao Paulo.
dans les appelés formes plus plaines de capitalisme.
Capitalism established new social relations of production.
Bien, le capitalisme arrive avec des nouvelles relations sociales de production.
A new workforce is necessary to comply with that. That's the reason of
une nouvelle force de travail est nécessaire. Delà le projet d'immigration
the immigration project, which is meant to whiten the population.
pour blanchir la population.
The impact of the gentrification process on the indigenous and black populations
Le procès de gentrification des noirs et de la population indigène
is historical and it's still ongoing.
est continu et historique.
The very same process, for over 500 years.
Il y a plus de 500 ans, le même procès.